The Crocodile,
the Crab,
Bobbin,
the Flying Dustbin,
and Mulberry.
Confidential names for the specially
devised weapons that will help the
Allies defeat Hitler's deadly defenses
on D-Day.
>> If it goes wrong, they're stuck on the
beaches.
This absolutely had to work.
>> Now on World's Weirdest Weapons, the
untold stories of the machines that gave
the edge to the Allies in the greatest
amphibious assault in history.
>> [music]
>> It's November 1943,
and for the Allies, the outcome of the
Second World War is hanging in the
balance.
If the Allied leaders are to secure the
upper hand, they will need more than
just their standard armory.
They know that if they're finally to
defeat Hitler, a program to develop a
whole new generation of weapons is
essential.
US President Franklin D. Roosevelt and
British Prime Minister Winston Churchill
set in motion secret plans for an
audacious assault on a 50-mi long
stretch of beaches in northern France in
an area called Normandy.
>> Hitler knew that the Allies would at
some time try to invade.
And so, his plan was to build what he
called the Atlantic Wall.
That was a continuous line of defense
and right from the top of Norway
right the way down to the Spanish
border.
>> Adolf Hitler has assigned his finest
general, Field Marshal Erwin Rommel, to
supervise the construction of a vast and
terrifying band of Atlantic
fortifications.
>> The concept was to provide concrete
bunkers,
concrete artillery positions,
mines on sticks to obstruct landing
craft.
>> Rommel immediately brings in 260,000
men to reinforce [music] 15,000 strong
points along the French coast
and embarks on his plan for a zone of
death
requiring the laying of 200 million
mines together with all kinds of
artificial obstacles.
>> There were barbed wire entanglements.
There were pieces of Rommel's asparagus.
Iron girders that were put there to stop
troops and tanks and invading vehicles
and getting up the beaches.
>> For the Allied commanders, this presents
a huge problem.
An amphibious attack is the most
dangerous and unpredictable means of
invasion.
And they must find a way to land enough
men and firepower to hold the beaches
long enough to establish a bridgehead.
With the invasion slated for summer
1944,
they know they have only a few months to
find a solution.
To solve the problem, the Allies turn to
Percy Hobart.
>> Hobart was a brilliant tank man in the
First World War
and he knew more about tanks
and how they operated and how they
should be operated brilliantly than
anybody else in the British Army.
>> Percy Hobart had made his name in Egypt
in the 1930s, where he created the 7th
Armoured Division, later famously known
as the Desert Rats.
But his obsession with tanks put him out
of favor with fellow generals.
>> Hobart actually gets a bit of a
reputation as being a prickly character
because he is very sure of his own
opinions and he's [music] also an
excellent teacher. So he influences
quite a number of people, but he treads
on a number of toes during the process
of his advancement through the military
hierarchy.
>> Hobart's unpopularity sees him sent back
to England in 1939. [music]
But a little over a year before the
invasion, Churchill puts the 57-year-old
in charge of the secret weapons program.
[music]
>> Churchill said, "Look, what we need are
some brutal new weapons which will do
the enemy some
great deal of harm."
And Churchill gave him a more or less
free hand.
>> In preparation for the assault, Hobart
heads up a specialist tank team,
the 79th Armoured Division, and
immediately makes an impression.
>> Hobart is such a great trainer of men.
He's very enthusiastic to also hear
ideas from the whole spectrum of his
unit.
Hobart is just [music] as happy to take
the advice from a driver of a vehicle
who thinks he knows how they might come
up against one of these problems better.
>> I'm the ugly one.
There.
>> Ian Hammerton is a lieutenant in the
army when he works alongside Hobart
during testing.
>> This is my helmet.
Divisional sign, 79th Armoured Div.
And that's what it looks like on.
>> He was very much hands-on. He didn't
stand fools gladly.
But we all thought the world of him.
We thought he was
really the tops.
He was full of ideas.
>> Under intense secrecy, Hobart sets about
devising and building a whole host of
strange mechanical beasts to breach all
kinds of deadly barriers.
>> [music]
>> The first obstacle Hobart needs to
overcome, though, is [music] a natural
one.
The sea.
How do you get enough firepower onto the
shore quickly enough to assist the first
wave of troops?
>> It was the idea that when the infantry
touched down on the beaches, they should
not land unsupported.
They have rifles,
>> [music]
>> machine guns,
mortars.
Not really the kind of weapons which you
can fight somebody hiding behind
concrete.
>> [music]
>> They needed tanks on the beaches.
>> So, Hobart creates a tank that can swim.
>> The point was that as soon as you
landed, you had these tanks with you
with their guns that could take on enemy
machine guns, enemy bunkers, and could
provide the heavy firepower you needed.
>> The plan is to launch the amphibious
tanks from landing craft sitting
offshore.
It's a good idea, but how do you get a
heavy tank to float?
And then, how do you get it to swim up
to a distance of a mile onto the beach?
>> [music]
>> As security and secrecy is paramount, a
secluded area on the east coast of
England is chosen for the swimming tanks
development.
To begin with, the team must make a tank
waterproof.
They surround its hull with a large and
tightly fastened canvas.
For buoyancy, the canvas is raised
around [music] the tank deck with the
help of rubber tubing filled with
compressed air.
This will allow its colossal weight to
float.
Testing begins with the British
Valentine tank, but it isn't very
adaptable and it's primarily used for
training.
But the American Sherman proves perfect
for the task.
It's a large tank and there's lots of
them available.
The question is how to get all 30 tons
of it to swim.
David Willey is the curator at the Tank
Museum in Bovington.
Once a training base for Hobart, and now
the home of many of his inventions.
[music]
Including the adapted American tank, the
Duplex Drive.
>> The rear of this DD Sherman or Duplex
Drive Sherman, we can see what it's all
about, really. Duplex Drive cuz it can
drive for two ways. One, it can drive on
its tracks on the ground.
The other way is by these propellers
that we can see down here.
>> With the propellers retracted for normal
land use, by a simple change of gearing
on leaving a landing craft, the
propellers can be easily activated,
enabling the tank to move at a speed of
up to four knots in the water.
Carrying a crew of five, the Sherman DD
tests well.
On April the 18th, 1944, the DDs are
presented to the commander of land
forces for the invasion, General Bernard
Montgomery.
He's so impressed, it's decided the DDs
will definitely lead the assault on
D-Day.
As a result, 500 new swimming tanks are
commissioned.
But having worked out how to get tanks
from the sea onto the shore, Hobart and
his team now have a heap of other
problems to overcome.
Like how to get his tanks up the
beaches.
The problem is the sand.
Tanks have a habit of getting stuck in
sand [music] and shingle.
Hobart needs to ensure this doesn't
happen during the invasion.
>> [music]
>> The allies conduct some research to help
get to the bottom [music] of the
problem.
>> What the Brits did was to send over
small submarines
with teams of investigators [music]
at night who actually got onto the
beaches of Normandy, ran ashore with
condoms, and collected soil samples in
the condoms, and then took them back to
Britain for analysis.
>> The discovery [music] of soft blue clay
on the Normandy beaches gives Hobart's
team a starting point.
>> Straight away, the problem was put
[music] to Hobart. How are we going to
get our armored vehicles across this
soft blue clay?
What they come up [music] with is
actually something called Bobbin. The
Bobbin is a mat-laying device for
crossing soft ground on beaches or
marsh.
>> The Bobbin is an adaptation [music]
of the British Churchill Armoured
Vehicle Royal Engineers, better known as
AVRE.
It has [music] thick armor, and like the
American Sherman, can be easily
modified.
>> A Bobbin tank would lay down a path or
carpet of material over the sand to
provide just that little bit of extra
strength to enable a heavy vehicle to
come ashore very early on in the
landings.
>> [music]
>> The Bobbin's job is to provide the
necessary traction on the Normandy sand
and a fast and efficient stream of
armored vehicles up the beaches.
It may look clumsy, but the Bobbin
typifies what would become the team's
very practical approach to
problem-solving,
and is one of what will become known as
Hobart's Funnies.
>> Sometimes, if it's just a matter of
welding a bits of metal girders
together. If it's effective, that's good
enough for Hobart. It doesn't have to
look beautiful. It has to do a job on a
certain day at a certain key moment in
time.
>> But the next challenge Hobart faces is
even tougher and requires even greater
ingenuity.
How to advance men and their artillery
over and through the myriad of beach
defenses.
Rommel has already planted millions of
mines on beaches and in minefields
running up to 6 mi inland and along the
entire French coast.
The traditional way of dealing with
mines, with bayonets and metal
detectors, is slow and it's dangerous.
>> [music]
>> The allies need a safer and faster
method of mine clearance. [music]
So Hobart comes up with a flail tank.
The flail is an adaptation of the
successful Matilda Scorpion mine
sweeping tank that has been used in
North Africa.
The Scorpion uses a front mounted device
with chains to deliberately detonate
mines in its path.
But it has its disadvantages.
It doesn't carry a gun.
Recognizing the need for firepower,
Hobart adapts the American Sherman.
By ensuring that the tank's gun remains,
its effectiveness as a battle tank isn't
compromised.
But as an armored vehicle, it's a
difficult thing to master.
Ian Hammerton is given the new mine
clearing tanks to take back to his
cavalry regiment.
>> We had two of these flails and it was a
question of practicing and finding out
how to do it.
The only bit of flat ground, of course,
was the cricket pitch. So, we were not
very popular with the city fathers.
However, we told them there's a war on.
>> Hobart's flail becomes known as the
Sherman Crab.
>> This is the Sherman Crab or flail tank.
These chains on this drum on the front
of the vehicle, when this vehicle goes
into action to flail or beat the ground,
this drum is rotated. Power is taken off
the engines. This drum spins round and
these chains beat the ground.
>> That is the bottom end of the
flail chain.
The whole thing would be about 5 ft
long.
It would be whirling round and smiting
into the ground to a depth of up to 15
in and
and hopefully striking a mine.
>> [music]
>> The Sherman Crab doesn't just deal with
mines.
It's also effective against another
particularly vicious obstacle the allies
know they will face on the Normandy
beaches.
Barbed wire.
>> [music]
>> German barbed wire is nasty stuff.
It's got lots of prickles on it.
The flail was very useful for cutting
through barbed wire entanglements.
>> They designed this drum that when it
goes around, it will either rip off
barbed wire, but these are on the edges,
these end up acting like cutters and
they will rip off any barbed wire as
well.
>> [music]
>> Once through the wire, the advancing
tanks and infantry now have another
challenge.
>> [music]
>> Well, the allies had carried out
extensive reconnaissance
of the Atlantic Wall, taking
photographs.
They had developed contacts with the
French Resistance, the Maquis, to
provide them with often quite detailed
information.
>> Hobart knows the allies will face an
enemy who are well dug in behind large
walls, pillboxes, and gun [music]
emplacements.
>> They needed a short-range gun that was
big and powerful and could blow its way
through concrete [music]
in order to be able to take out the
German defensive positions on the
beaches.
>> Hobart's solution is the Petard Mortar.
>> The purpose of the Petard is the
destruction of concrete obstacles.
>> You had a short sort of stubby little
muscle.
It fired a special bomb in effect.
About this distance, 80 to 230 yd.
And it was a brilliant weapon.
>> The Petard's [music] bomb is given the
nickname Flying Dustbin.
>> Such a large amount of explosives was
put in there. It has a small tail on it.
The tail contains an explosive charge.
And the idea is is once it's loaded a
rod [music]
rams up the back of this tail
sets off the charge, that flies this
dustbin full of explosive out the front
of the vehicle.
It's very, very effective.
>> The Petard is the culmination of a range
of weaponry designed to swim, flail, and
blast the allies onto the Normandy
beaches.
But now Hobart and his team must
overcome another challenge. How to
tackle the German enemy hidden in
pillboxes.
For this, Hobart has a brutal weapon up
his sleeve.
>> The most terrible, awful [music] weapon
of all was the Crocodile, the flame
throwers.
>> The Crocodile's purpose is [music] to
drive the enemy out of their gunning
placements and bunkers.
And as landing troops fight their way up
and off the beaches, they will repel and
terrify any German defenders.
>> It was a Churchill tank
with a special gun which would eject a
mixture of oil and other combustible
[music] elements
a distance of up to 230 yd.
>> The Churchill Crocodile toes an armored
trailer filled with nearly 2,000 L of
liquid fuel.
Actually, an early form of napalm.
It's squirted through the vehicle
towards a jet at the front of [music]
the tank.
A spark then ignites the petrol creating
a flame which leaps [music] towards the
enemy.
Next, Hobart and his team have to figure
out a way to get troops off the beaches,
over the sea wall, and beyond.
If a concrete barrier can't be
demolished, it has to be climbed.
>> The Churchill tank could take a small
Bailey bridge on top.
It seems incredible.
And once it got to the right place,
it just discarded
the bridge, and everybody could roll
over that stream, that small river,
whatever it happened to be.
>> [music]
>> The bridge layer is the first of
Hobart's breakout weapons.
Rommel has created a network of ditches
and specially dug anti-tank trenches,
flooded or booby-trapped with mines and
explosives.
So, for this, [music] Hobart's team
devised the fascine.
>> Fascine tanks have been around since the
First World War,
where the fascines were used to [music]
block trenches in the advance.
>> This version [music] carries a bundle of
branches, enabling vehicles to drive up
and over sea walls, and to bridge
ditches.
>> They would turn the [music] turret to
the side, put a massive fascine, that's
bundles of twigs together that were held
on by wires. If there's a gap or a shell
hole ahead of you,
pull the lever, that cuts the wires,
[music]
the fascine drops in in hole, and the
tanks and the following vehicles can go
over it.
>> Hobart's team rehearse and rehearse.
They know that the success of the
advance in land will be heavily reliant
on how quickly Rommel's obstacles can be
breached.
>> By now, such is the great interest in
finding ways of breaking Hitler's
Atlantic Wall, others come in on the
act.
>> The Admiralty had their Department of
Miscellaneous Weapons Development, and
they were determined to keep up with
these crazy ideas that the army were
looking at.
>> Nevil Shute, who will later become
famous as a novelist, is a department
head in the British Admiralty's Special
Weapons Unit.
His daughter Heather remembers her
father's highly classified work.
>> I was about 10 [snorts]
to 12, [music] I guess.
He was working in in his office in
London on sort of going out on trials
and things.
It was secret, and that was partly why I
knew so little of it.
>> With a background in aeronautical
engineering, Shute comes up with an
innovative weapon to breach [music] the
wall.
Designed to penetrate a concrete barrier
of up to 10 ft high and 7 ft wide, its
name is the Great Panjandrum.
>> This was going to be a kind of a
Catherine wheel.
Think of it as being a vast cotton reel.
Two rims surrounded by rockets, 10 ft in
diameter, and carrying a ton of
explosives.
>> Propelled by its cordite rockets,
Panjandrum carries a 4,000-lb payload.
Intended to achieve speeds of around 60
mph, it's designed to smash into an
obstacle and blow it to pieces.
When they tried to launch it, of course,
it didn't create much power.
The trouble with putting the rockets
around the wheels meant that you had as
many rockets blowing backwards as
forwards, and you had as many rockets
blowing upwards and downwards.
It wobbled along the beach, fell on one
side, broke into bits. People were
almost killed by these crazy rockets
shooting [music] off in all directions.
Despite its obvious flaws during tests,
on the 12th of January, 1944,
the Great Panjandrum is put before the
Admiralty's top brass.
>> They started that Great Panjandrum
rolling down the beach.
Well, one of the admirals had a dog,
and the grand great [music] Panjandrum,
it must have sensed the dog there and
didn't like the dog cuz it did a turn
like that and went barreling after the
dog instead of going down the beach.
But the dog escaped and and the grand
the great Panjandrum died a death.
>> [laughter]
[music]
>> Perhaps, understandably, watching
Americans don't want anything to do with
these newfangled weapons and decide to
use only the DD floating tank based on
their own Sherman for the invasion.
Instead, their training goes ahead using
more conventional weapons.
>> They were reluctant in some areas,
understandably, to retrain lots of
soldiers on British vehicles such as the
Churchill, which they'd be very
unfamiliar with.
>> The whole approach of the Americans was
to regard the funnies as as an
unnecessary burden. Britain, who sort of
made them and invented them, and and we
put our heart and soul into them, we
were much more confident that they'd
work.
>> But US forces are won over by another
idea prompted by a failed invasion 2
years before.
>> In 1942,
the British had tried
to see what happened. Could they capture
a port by surprise? They had picked the
port of Dieppe.
And it had been a disaster.
>> When the British had attempted [music]
to seize the French port of Dieppe,
they'd found it heavily defended.
More than 2/3 of the 6,000 largely
Canadian troops [music] were killed,
injured, or captured by the Germans.
The experience convinced the allies to
avoid trying to take a port again.
But without an efficient [music] way of
getting reinforcements and supplies on
shore, any sustained assault on France
against such massive German opposition
>> [music]
>> is bound to fail.
The British, however, have a solution.
>> [music]
>> They were going to do something which
had never been done before in the whole
of military history. They were going to
prefabricate a port and take it with
them.
>> We realized that if we were going to
land troops on the Normandy beaches,
there would have to be a dock. And so
they invented the floating Mulberry
harbor.
>> In October 1943,
Churchill instructs a labor force of
45,000
in shipyards across the length and
breadth of Britain to begin construction
of nearly 150 steel and concrete
caissons,
some as much as 200 ft long and five
stories high.
They also build 19 floating piers, 6 mi
of steel roadway, and more than 300
massive steel and concrete floats.
During construction, the component parts
[music] are covertly sunk in rivers,
estuaries, and sea locks in order to
hide them from German reconnaissance.
>> The secrecy of the Mulberry Harbor was
crucially important.
A lot of companies were each just given
instructions on what they were building,
but they didn't know what the whole
thing was going to be. They simply
followed the designs and produced the
product.
We knew that if word ever got out to
Germany, that that would blow the whole
of our plan.
>> In the last vital hours before the
assault, all the parts of the Mulberries
will be refloated and made ready for the
perilous voyage to the Normandy beaches.
But as the different parts of the
Mulberries have never actually been
assembled, no one knows if the audacious
[music] plan will work.
As D-Day approaches, Allied troops make
their final preparations.
They're counting on risky and untested
innovations like the Mulberries and
Hobart's Funnies to ensure the success
of the invasion.
It's a huge gamble.
>> If it failed, it could probably not be
remounted
perhaps for several months, perhaps in
the politics of the time, not at all.
This absolutely had to work.
>> Dawn.
6th of June, 1944.
D-Day.
The Allied veil of secrecy has proved
effective.
Hitler has no idea an invasion is
planned for Normandy.
An armada of more than 5,000 ships and
landing craft are approaching the coast
of France.
On board they're carrying a host of
specialist weaponry designed to break
through the German defenses.
For the assault troops, bad weather
conditions have meant a long
uncomfortable journey from England in
rough seas.
Flail tank commander Ian Hammerton is
amongst those in the English Channel.
>> I felt terrible.
In fact, before I dished out the maps, I
was seasick over the stern.
We were passing through all the
merchant ships that were waiting
to unload infantry.
And suddenly my seasickness disappeared.
>> As the first of the 156,000
troops preparing for battle make their
approach to the beaches, it's also time
for Hobart's secret weapons to go into
action.
First up are the floating tanks.
Sherman DDs containing [music] British,
American, and Canadian troops lead the
amphibious invasion force.
They are launched at varying distances
[music] from the shore and with varying
success.
>> About 200 were deployed.
Of course, the closer
they could get to the shore,
the better.
Because if it was a rough sea, they
could easily be swamped.
>> On the British beach code named Sword
and the American beach [music] Utah, a
total of 64 DDs are launched less than a
mile out and all but four make it
ashore.
As predicted, German defenders are
baffled by the DDs and they're virtually
ignored.
>> There's an account of one of the British
[music] soldiers seeing a German machine
gunner stand up with his mouth open in
absolute awe of this vehicle that's just
suddenly arrived in front of him.
>> As the DDs arrive and drop their
canvases, they unleash a barrage of fire
on the beaches.
But at Omaha Beach, Americans launched
their DDs 3 miles from shore
and the results are catastrophic.
>> It was bad up cuz the weather was a bit
rougher, the sea was a bit rougher.
>> Strong currents spin many of the tanks
sideways on, parallel to the beach.
The canvas skirts, which have been
designed to hit foot-high waves head-on,
are rendered useless [music] as waves of
up to 6 ft fill up the tanks on their
sides.
Of the 30 destined for Omaha, only three
reach their target.
The remainder sink.
Back on the British and Canadian
beaches, it's time for the next group of
secret weapons.
Churchill AVRE Petards join the DDs
already attacking large beach obstacles,
German gun positions, and the sea wall.
>> So, the bombards were in great demand
bashing the hell out of all the concrete
defenses.
>> One 14-lb Petard bomb would normally
blow a house down.
That's how powerful they were.
>> Having softened the enemy, the
specialist weapons now have to get
through the beach defenses.
Commander Ian Hamilton is part of the
first wave at Juno Beach and experiences
them firsthand.
>> There was a lot of beach to cover
and there were a lot of obstacles, all
of which were
equipped with some sort of explosive.
>> Again, Hobart's arsenal goes into
action.
With obstacles being blasted, Sherman
Crabs clear barbed wire and flail to
enable troops to get to possible exit
points at the top of the beaches.
Troops need to force a breakout into the
Normandy towns and countryside beyond.
It's now that the battle reaches a
critical stage.
>> It's like trying to force toothpaste
through a tube. There's only so many
troops you can land in a given area
rapidly enough to maintain that kind of
momentum.
If it goes wrong, if they stall, they
are stuck on the beaches and that is
where the troops would have died.
>> Crucially, where Hobart's weapons are
used on the British and Canadian
beaches, they prove valuable.
>> There was enough specialized armor
to actually advance through the initial
German defenses.
Enough flail tanks to flail past up
across the beach to get to the seawall.
Enough box girder bridges put in place,
so they were vital to actually opening
out the German defenses for the main
body of tanks and infantry break
through.
>> 18-year-old Royal Engineer George Batt
lands on Gold Beach as part of the
second wave.
>> There's a flails,
the flamethrowers,
the ones with bridges on that came over.
And
fences or fencings, something like that.
Fascines, that's right.
They were crude-looking,
but by God, they were effective.
>> But this success is not mirrored
everywhere.
On Omaha Beach, where only Percy
Hobart's swimming tanks have been
deployed, the failure to land the
majority of them has been costly.
Partly due to this lack of critical
early firepower, hundreds of US infantry
landing on the heavily defended beach
have been left stranded.
Many have been left exposed to the enemy
amidst the vicious wire and obstacles.
By the end of D-Day,
more than 4,000 men, mostly Americans,
have been killed.
But despite this, the initial invasion
has been a success.
More than 150,000
Allied troops have secured a narrow
beachhead in Normandy.
Now ashore, the Allies need to keep
their troops supplied.
It's time for the Mulberries.
Winston Churchill's floating harbor plan
quickly swings into action.
By the afternoon of D-Day, the first of
a series of ships are sunk to form a
breakwater.
But the Allies still don't know if the
Mulberries are going to work.
>> From positions still along the coast of
the Allies have not yet captured, the
Germans can see the first stages of the
Mulberry harbors being built.
And they never really understand what it
is they are looking at.
>> They're not the only ones.
Sapper George Batts is told that he'll
be working on the [music] Mulberries.
>> We didn't know what they were.
We'd seen things being towed over by
tugs and that.
There was all sorts of rumors went
around about them.
It was said that they were going to be
put together to make landing for
aircraft.
We were going to live on them, sleep on
them. We weren't privy to any
information. We were just told what we
wanted to and get on with it.
>> Within 10 days, [music] two Mulberry
Harbors, code-named A and B, are
constructed at Omaha Beach and Gold
Beach.
But not everything [music] goes to plan.
>> There was a bad storm a few days after
D-Day.
>> It was one heck of a storm.
I was on the Mulberry Harbor when it
started.
And believe me, it was frightening.
And it went on for I think 3 days, I
think.
The American Mulberry was smashed to
smithereens.
>> The storm, the worst to be seen on the
Normandy coast for 40 years, leaves
Mulberry [music] A at Omaha beyond
repair.
But while B at [music] Gold Beach is
also severely damaged, it's salvaged and
patched up sufficiently enough for it to
become a vital means of support for
[music] the Allied advance.
George Batts is [music] ordered to work
daily 12-hour shifts loading and
unloading equipment and supplies.
>> All the vehicles came along here.
Making it one-way [music] circuit.
Out to the unloading portion at the end.
Mulberry Harbor was really three parts.
There was one special one for
ammunition.
And then there was one built for ingoing
traffic, which was about a mile long. At
the end of that was where the ships
pulled in.
There was everything coming off, all
stores, ammunition, food,
the troops,
you name it.
>> Mulberry B also provides a quick and
efficient way to ferry out the injured
and German prisoners of war.
Allied troops watch their departure.
>> They were the drag with lot.
Bit of jealousy I suppose because they
were coming home and we're still there.
>> In all, the Mulberries successfully land
2 and 1/2 million men,
500,000 [music] vehicles, and a total of
4 million tons of supplies.
And it's not until the Allies capture
the port of Antwerp in Belgium [music]
that Mulberry B is decommissioned 6
months after D-Day.
Hobart's arsenal of secret weapons,
meanwhile, continues to prove
indispensable for the remainder of the
Second World War.
In the months following the invasion,
inland intensive battles rage on as
Hitler's armies [music] still attempt
fierce counterattacks.
>> [music]
>> The majority of the specialist armor is
at the heart of the Allied [music]
advance.
>> They may need a box girder bridge or a
fascine dropped in a trench ditch so
they can proceed forward, sometimes with
a flamethrower, the Churchill Crocodile.
That may [music] come forward.
>> The Churchill Crocodile was the one
weapon that the Allies found that the
Germans had no answer to and would
surrender to if faced by it.
>> Anywhere where it was necessary
against a farmhouse with very thick
walls, and you get those all over
Normandy, where the enemy had taken up a
defensive position and deep defenses, a
short-range mortar shot from a Petard
mortar could be used.
>> Beyond Normandy, Hobart's specialist
armor continues to play its part.
>> They were very successful in Holland,
where we came across a huge amount of
mines.
>> Patrick Delaforce is with the 11th armor
division when it advances through
Normandy, onwards through France, and
into Holland.
He sees firsthand Hobart's specialist
tanks being deployed more and more
strategically.
>> It was a game which
the generals commanding each division
would pick whatever was needed from
these marvelous weapons of many
destruction.
They might say, "Right, tomorrow at
Cassino, we've got problems for you.
Tomorrow, we've got two more streams
which need a small Bailey, so bad luck,
you've got to fit up tonight."
So, they often had to work throughout
the night to prepare for the next day's
battle.
>> Hobart's 79th division and crocodiles,
along with Petards and flails, proved
decisive in the capture of the French
port of Le Havre in September [music]
1944.
In March 1945,
>> [music]
>> it's in swimming tanks that British
troops triumphantly cross the Rhine into
Germany.
And 2 months later, crocodiles are used
to [music] raise to the ground the
typhus-ridden shell of Hitler's
concentration camp Bergen-Belsen.
With brutal battles still raging [music]
in the Pacific until August 1945,
American troops go on to use their own
versions of flamethrowers and amphibious
tanks in Okinawa to help defeat the
Japanese.
>> [music]
>> But it's for the contribution to the
Allied invasion of France in 1944,
the largest amphibious assault [music]
ever attempted, that Percy Hobart's
unique weapons are best remembered.
[music]
>> I don't want to give the impression that
they were the overwhelming [music] key
to success of D-Day because they
weren't.
But they did everything that Hobart said
they [music] would. They met all the
challenges that they should.
>> The problem of how to get quickly in
land in order not to get trapped from
the beaches
was a critical issue of D-Day.
The funnies were a large part of the
solution.
>> The most daring invasion plan of the
entire war was made possible because of
these unique weapons, which so
effectively [music]
outsmarted the German defenses.
Had they not been employed with such
devastating [music]
effect,
many more Allied lives would have been
lost on the path to victory.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Oh.